(upbeat music)
- Hello, English learners.
Welcome back to another
great podcast here at English pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we're gonna be talking
about one of our favorite topics as always.
- Food.
- Food, we're gonna be at a restaurant.
- And you know, one of the most difficult
or embarrassing things
to deal with at a restaurant
is what to say when you don't like
the food, or when it's bad quality food.
- Right, so maybe we
have to complain about
the food, or maybe
even the service, right?
- That's right, and in this lesson,
we're going to be learning
some really wonderful words
and phrases that you can
use when you need to complain
about the food or the
service in a restaurant.
- Okay, so before we listen to what
happens in this restaurant with this food,
let's take a look very
quickly at vocabulary preview.
- Very cabaret-y preview.
- Okay, we're only gonna do
one word today, and this you'll
hear in the dialogue, an
establishment establishment.
- This kind of establishment.
- Okay, so when I say an establishment,
that's a noun, what is an establishment?
- It's basically a fancy word for a
business or a restaurant in this case.
- In this case, it's a restaurant.
- Yeah.
- But in general, you can say it's a business,
so you have a very fine establishment.
- That's right, so an establishment, a type
of business, a place of business, really.
- Very good.
All right, so now it's time for
us to listen to our dialogue.
We're gonna find out what's going on here.
Apparently, there is a very angry
customer, and we're gonna find out why.
(upbeat music)
- Excuse me, waiter.
- Yes, sir, what can I do for you?
- I've been sitting here
for the past 20 minutes,
and no one has offered me a
glass of water, brought any bread
to the table, and our appetizer
haven't been served yet.
You know, in this kind of establishment,
I'd expect much better service.
- I'm sorry, sir, I'll check
on your order right away.
- For a lax honey, the
place is busy tonight,
and I've heard the
food is amazing, anyway.
- Here you are, sir, the fog off of the
lady, and a mushroom soup for you.
- Wait, sir, I heard a cream of
mushroom soup with asparagus.
This soup is obviously too
runny, and it's over-seasoned.
It's completely inedible.
- Okay, I do apologize for that.
Can I bring you another soup, or
would you like to order something else?
- Take this flock high back as well.
It's rubbery and completely overcooked.
And look at the portion size.
- How can you charge
$25 for a sliver of duck liver?
- Right away, sir.
- Honey, come on, the fog I was fine.
Why are you making such a big deal?
Are you trying to get
our meal pumped again?
- What do you mean?
- You're paying for this, and I'm
showing out my hard-earned bucks.
I expect value for money.
- Here you are, sir.
I hope it is all right now.
The chef has prepared
it, especially for you.
- Yes, fine.
Why are you whole, right?
(sighs)
- Well, I guess that's one lesson.
Hey, if you're in a restaurant,
don't be too rude to the waiter.
You never know what's gonna happen.
- The waiter and the cook, right?
- Yeah, you don't wanna
offend that kitchen staff.
- All right, so we'll talk
about that a little bit later on,
but now I think we had some
really interesting vocabulary
of how to describe food
that is not well-prepared,
and we can take a look at
that now in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- All right, so the guy in this
dialogue, he ordered a mushroom soup,
and he complained that the
mushroom soup was too runny.
- Okay, the soup is too runny.
- Runny.
- So he wanted a cream of mushroom,
so it should be a little bit thicker.
- Yep.
- But in this case, it was runny.
- So when something
is runny, it's too liquid.
- Too liquid.
And I think we can relate
it to a runny nose, right?
- Exactly.
- Okay, so when liquid is
coming out of your nose,
a runny nose, in this
case, the soup is runny.
- All right, and another thing
that he was complaining about,
the food was over-seasoned.
- Over-seasoned.
- The food is over-seasoned.
- Okay, so if the food is
over-seasoned, it's too salty.
So it's another way
of saying it's too salty.
- Yeah, it's kind of a fancy cooking term.
- Now, can I say, if
there's too much pepper
in the food, can I say
it's over-seasoned?
- Well, technically no.
When a cook says something is
over-seasoned, he's talking salt only.
- Only salt, okay.
So the cream of mushroom is very runny.
It's over-seasoned and he
said it's completely inedible.
- Inedible.
- It's inedible.
Now, this word edible, you can eat it.
You can eat it.
So we add this prefix inedible.
- You cannot eat it.
- This is not possible.
- Yeah, and it doesn't mean
that physically you can't eat it.
It just means it's pretty disgusting.
- Okay, this food is inedible.
- Mm-hmm.
- And then he started to
complain about the other dish
and he said that it's rubbery.
- Rubbery, the forgrap was rubbery.
- All right.
So I think we noticed the word rubber.
- Mm-hmm.
- So obviously if a
food is rubbery, it tastes,
or it's too chewy, it's like chewing
on the bottom of your shoe, right?
- Okay, so it's too hard
to chew or to swallow.
- Exactly.
- All right.
Apparently, the food was rubbery
because it's completely overcooked.
- Overcooked.
- All right, we have overcooked.
So when something is overcooked,
I mean, it's easy to
understand that it's cooked too
much, but it doesn't
mean that it's burnt, right?
- No, so maybe you've ordered your steak
to be rare, but it comes to you well done.
So it's not burnt, but
it's cooked too much.
- So also I guess we can say like chicken,
sometimes if you overcook
chicken, it comes out to dry.
- Yep.
- All right, so to overcook something.
- And finally he was
complaining about the size
of the dish and he said,
this is a sliver of duck liver.
- Okay, a sliver.
- A sliver.
- All right, now this word
sliver is like a slice, right?
- A very small, tiny little slice.
- Okay, so we can say, okay, I just
want a sliver of bacon for breakfast.
- All right, why don't we hear a few
more examples of how we can use sliver?
- Example one.
No, John's on a diet.
He'll just have a sliver
of cake and no ice cream.
- Example two.
- I'm really full, but
it looks so delicious.
Can you just cut me a sliver?
- Example three.
- You call this sliver of
beef on my plate of meal?
There's almost nothing here.
- And those are all the words
we had for language takeaway.
Now you have, so we've
given you different adjectives
of describing food that
is not well-prepared.
So now let's move on to some other phrases
that the customer used to
complain in fluency builder.
- Fluency builder.
Okay, so before we get to the
customer complaining language,
I wanna look at a phrase that
the waiter used to apologize.
He said, I do apologize.
- I do apologize. - I do apologize.
- Now, why is this phrase so interesting?
- Well, I mean, it's pretty easy
to understand the meaning,
but I wanna look at why
he added this verb due.
Well, he added the verb due to this phrase
to make it seem a little bit stronger,
to give it a little more
power to his apology.
- Right, so if you have an affirmative
phrase, like I apologize, it's good,
but if you wanna give it a little bit more
emphasis, you can say I do apologize.
- Why don't we give an example?
So I might say this.
- Marco, I didn't know
we had a party tonight.
- And I might say, what?
I did tell you about it last week.
- Right, so you're
just giving a little bit
more power to the
statement that you told me.
So this due did does, it
becomes an auxiliary to
make it more powerful,
to give it more emphasis.
- Yeah, exactly.
So a neat little phrase,
something you can use,
if you wanna make your apologies
sound, maybe a little bit stronger.
- All right, now moving
on to the next phrase,
he was complaining about
the food and it was terrible,
and he said, I'm shelling
out my hard-earned bucks.
- Okay, let's break this
one down into two sections.
We'll start with shelling out.
- All right, so to shell out.
So when you shell out,
you pay for something.
- All right, but this gives you the
sensation that you don't really want to pay.
- You're a bit unhappy about it.
- Right, so you wanna shell out your money.
- Mm-hmm, why don't
we listen to some examples
to show us how we can
use this phrase to shell out.
Example one.
- Great, it's my girlfriend's
birthday this month.
So I'm gonna have to
shell out for a present.
- Example two.
I really want those shoes, but I
can't really afford to shell out $400.
Example three.
I can't believe it, Ella showed
out the $800 for the tickets.
I thought I would have to pay.
- All right, so now that
we understand shell out,
let's move on to the
second part of that sentence.
My hard-earned bucks.
- Hard-earned bucks.
- Okay, so bucks are dollars, right?
- Dollars, only dollars, right?
- Yeah, not pounds, not euros,
but his hard-earned bucks is
money he had to work really hard for.
So I can also save my
hard-earned money, right?
Or my hard-earned cash.
- Exactly.
- Very good, so you worked hard to get it.
- All right, so three great
phrases that can be used
when you're complaining in a
restaurant, and why don't we hear
them one last time in context
by listening to the dialogue?
(upbeat music)
- Excuse me, waiter.
- Yes sir, what can I do for you?
- I've been sitting here
for the past 20 minutes
and no one has offered me a
glass of water, brought any bread
to the table, and our appetizer
haven't been served yet.
You know, in this kind of establishment,
I'd expect much better service.
- I'm sorry sir, I'll check
on your order right away.
- For a lax honey, the
place is busy tonight,
and I've heard the
food is amazing anyway.
- Here you are sir, the fog off of the
lady, and a mushroom soup for you.
- waiter, I heard a cream of mushroom soup
with asparagus, the soup
is obviously too runny
and it's over season,
it's completely inevitable.
- Okay, I do apologize for that.
Can I bring you another soup, or
would you like to order something else?
- Take this fog hot back as well.
It's rubbery and completely overcooked.
And look at the portion size.
How can you charge $25
for a sliver of duck liver?
- Right away sir.
- Honey, come on, the fog ride was fine.
Why are you making such a big deal?
Are you trying to get
our meal pumped again?
- What do you mean?
- You're paying for this, and I'm
shelling out my hard earned bucks.
- I expect value for money.
- Here you are sir, I
hope it is all right now.
The chef has prepared
it, especially for you.
- Yes, fine.
- Honey, are you whole right?
- No, no, no.
(upbeat music)
- So complaining at a restaurant
and actually sending food
back is not uncommon in the US.
- Yeah, of course, if the food's bad,
of course you're gonna send it back.
But maybe in other cultures,
I think people would be
a little bit more reluctant
to do something like this.
- Yeah, but hey, you
know what's an interesting
thing about the way
Americans eat in restaurants.
Sometimes at the end
of the meal, if they haven't
finished everything, they
might ask for a doggy bag.
- A doggy bag, yeah.
- So what is that a doggy bag?
- Well, usually if you order a big meal or
half your steak is leftover on the plate,
you would ask for a doggy bag and
it would bring you a little box or a bag
and you would take it to
supposedly give it to your dog.
- Right, so it's sort
of like you tell the
waiter, oh, you know,
the steak was so good,
I couldn't finish it, can I
take some home to my dog?
- Right, so you would just ask,
where can I have a doggy bag?
- Right, but it's sort of like code for,
I'm gonna eat this tomorrow for lunch.
- Exactly, because people
wouldn't really give it
to their dog, you know,
that steak wrapped up
in a fancy sort of foil swan is gonna
be pretty delicious the next day.
- Right, yeah, it's actually
very common in the US,
but in other countries, people will leave.
- Yeah.
- Entire plates of food like totally impolite
to ask the waiter to pack up the food for you.
- Exactly, yep.
- So a little bit of cultural differences,
but we wanna know what you think
and how things are done
maybe in your country
with complaining or sending food back
or even this whole doggy bag situation.
- That's right, why don't you
visit our website, EnglishPod.
com and tell us about it.
- All right, we'll be there
to answer any questions
or comments, but we gotta
go now, so until then, goodbye.
- Bye.
(upbeat music)